Thomas W. Gaines papers, Inclusive: 1861-1931, undated, Bulk: 1883-1893
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Thomas W. Gaines papers
Inclusive: 1861-1931, undated, Bulk: 1883-1893
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
1851
Gaines, Thomas W.
1 document box
The Thomas W. Gaines collection contains correspondence, legal and financial papers, military records, and books of military tactics from the American Civil War. Gaines was a Lieutenant Colonel in the 50th Illinois Infantry.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Thomas W. Gaines (1827-1894) from Quincey, Illinois, was a Lieutenant Colonel in the Union army's 50th Illinois Infantry during the American Civil War. Prior to the war, he married Eliza Ann Gaines (1840-1900). The couple had one son together, Thomas Wade Gaines (1861-1913). At some point after the war, the family moved to Clarksville, Texas, where Thomas W. Gaines passed away in 1894.
Scope and Content
The Thomas W. Gaines papers contain letters from after the Civil War, financial materials, lists of equipment issued to Gaines' Company D, 50th Illinois Infantry, and various collected and personal documents. No letters from during the Civil War are present in the collection. There are letters to and from other war veterans in the collection.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 1851. Acquired 1974-12-10
Related Resources
Related references
Find A Grave, Inc. "Thomas Wade Gaines." Memorial #6975693. Databases. Accessed 2020 July 17.
The American Civil War Research Database. "Soldier Data: Thomas W. Gaines." Alexander Street Press, LLC. Accessed 2020 July 17.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
United States. Army. Illinois Infantry Regiment, 50th (1861-1865).
Places
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Regimental histories.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Veterans.
Genres
Correspondence.; Financial records.
- Correspondence, 1871-1900; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Unknown.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains letters to and from Thomas W. Gaines, including correspondence he had with other veterans from the Civil War. This series is in average condition.
  - Letters, 1871-1872 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1873-1882 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1883-1888 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1890-1892 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1893-1900 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Financial, 1888-1931; 2
  This series contains bills and receipts from Gaines' life, primarily his time in Texas. This series is in average condition.
  - Bills and Receipts, 1888-1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Military Records, 1861-1862, undated; 3
  This series contains lists of equipment Gaines issued as captain of Company D, 50th Illinois Infantry, before his promotion to major and then lieutenant colonel. This series is in poor condition.
  - Equipment Issued to Company D, 50th Illinois Infantry, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - History of the 50th Illinois, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Infantry Tactics by Silas Casey, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Personal Materials, 1900-1917, undated; 4
  This series contains personal and collected materials from Thomas W. Gaines. The books listed are missing publication information, so the titles, date published, and author are unknown. This series is in average condition.
  - Song and Poem Books, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Religious Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - DeBerry Family, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, Textile Sample, Program, Photograph, 1900-1917 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pilot Grove Record, 1907 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 1)